Sam (Samantha) Freis, M.A.

Denver, CO • freis.sam@gmail.com • 214-240-3558 • www.sfreis.com • linkedin.com/in/sfreis/

PROFILE

Experienced researcher with 7+ years of experience in coordinating, designing, executing, and analyzing complex research projects to understand human behavior, cognition, and mental health. Proficient in various research methodologies, including experimental design, data collection, and statistical analysis. Strong communication skills and a demonstrated ability to present findings effectively. Collaborative team player who drives evidence-based decision-making and advances understanding of human behavior.

EXPERIENCE

Denver Museum of Nature and Science

April 2023 - Present

Research Assistant

Advanced the priorities of the Community Research and Evaluation Team by collecting visitor feedback and 200+ surveys

Project SHORT: Students for Higher Education Opportunities and Representation in Training

May 2022 - Present

Co-Director of Evaluation and Development & Mentor

- Measured the organization's success in providing mentorship and resources to prospective graduate students from
 underrepresented backgrounds by designing surveys in Qualtrics and gathering, triangulating, and analyzing qualitative and
 quantitative feedback from 1,000+ mentees and mentors
- Identified areas of improvement based on survey insights and presented suggested solutions to the executive board resulting in increased resources for international students, mentor recruitment in high demand disciplines, and additional programming

University of Colorado Boulder

August 2019 - Present

Graduate Researcher & Laboratory Instructor

- Produced 10 first-authored scientific publications and conference presentations using quantitative methods including hypothesis testing, descriptive, inferential, and multivariate statistical analysis, exploratory data analysis, model evaluation and interpretation, structural equation modeling, and data visualization
- Identified gaps in existing research, executed literature reviews, formulated study designs, conducted data management and Big Data wrangling, processed and analyzed behavioral and survey data, and prepared manuscripts
- Collaborated on projects with cross-functional research teams and stakeholders across 5+ departments and specialties resulting in 15 co-authored publications and presentations
- Synthesized, translated, and communicated research insights to diverse audiences through departmental presentations, invited talks, and interviews
- Awarded a <u>predoctoral training grant fellowship of \$150,000+</u> in tuition and stipend funding to advance knowledge on genetic and environmental influences on cognitive functions and mental health, a <u>\$2,000</u> award for Excellence in research, and an NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program Honorable Mention
- Delivered engaging instruction in behavioral science, research methods, experimental design, AB tests, the R programming language, and statistics to 60 students, achieving a 95% combined satisfaction rate

Population Research Center, University of Texas at Austin

May 2017 - June 2019

Research Coordinator & Project Manager

- Streamlined lab processes, improved data quality, and increased team productivity by developing a research coordinator manual, automating tasks with reproducible code, <u>managing 10+ databases in REDcap</u>, and executing data quality control
- Facilitated the development of a longitudinal cohort study by harmonizing multiple diverse databases and research protocols
- Recruited, trained, and <u>supervised a team of 20+ research assistants</u> across 6 semesters and summer sessions in ethical research practices, data collection, psychometric testing, data entry, and participant recruitment and scheduling
- · Developed a bi-weekly professional development newsletter to empower research assistant career advancement
- Handled budgetary tasks, ensured projects were in compliance with all funding agencies, and organized event planning

SKILLS

- R, SQL, Mplus, SPSS, MS Office
- Scientific writing and communication, leadership, teamwork, public speaking, grant writing, web copywriting

EDUCATION

University of Colorado Boulder, Boulder, CO

Ph.D., Psychology, Graduate Certificate in Quantitative Methods for Behavioral Sciences

University of Colorado Boulder, Boulder, CO

M.A., Psychology

The University of Texas at Austin, Austin, TX

B.S., Psychology, Biology Minor